okay we're ruined so we've we've covered
mushroom use for bioremediation and for
human health of course eating it is
already worth supporting human health
but which particular mushrooms would you
recommend to grow for local food
security you mentioned something about
little indie and mushrooms which have
been interesting to hear little bit more
about and the whole protein content of
mushroom story is quite interesting well
first let me go back to we just had
dinner the other night we had a we had a
vegetarian dinner who we had
chanterelles thank you fellows and pasta
and the chanterelles have about 15%
protein it's a wild mushroom when the
mushrooms are in season we're out
collecting them but the mushrooms we
collect in the season then we can grow
many of them all year round
so nature's the source of all strains so
while collecting mushrooms gives you a
great source complete amino acid
complexes but rich in vitamin B's and
they're all mushrooms called that are
wild that we've tested so far hyper
produced provided a pro vitamin d2 and
the mushrooms go from a very low vitamin
D content of what's about 40 to 50 IU's
of vitamin D one IU is I think 40
micrograms and the mushrooms go from you
know 40 or 50 IU's of vitamin D when
they're picked in October or so and
they're not exposed to direct sunlight
but if you put the mushrooms out even
dried from the previous year into the
Sun the full Sun for two days the
vitamin D goes from 50 IU's of vitamin D
to more than 40,000 per hundred grams
it's skyrockets vitamin D is an
essential vitamin and nutrient for your
immune system and at Harvard Medical
School of the University associated with
it they did a clinical study retro
actively looking at recovery from lung
cancer using conventional therapy lung
cancer recovery is very very low and
they found there was a four-fold
increase in lung cancer recovery when
the conventional treatments were given
in the summertime versus the wintertime
the only cofactor was vitamin D so
whatever strategy you have
improving human health the absence of
vitamin D lessons that ability for you
to benefit from it so the hyper
production of vitamin D in mushrooms
gives you more vitamin D than any
land-based organism so it's very
important that you know that for people
in the UK because and a person I just
managed to submitted the paper and he
compared mushroom vitamin D from vitamin
D in capsules and looking at the
absorption of vitamin D in the serum in
the blood and found a direct parallel
path dose response parallel to actually
taking a prescribed dose of vitamin D
and the vitamin D that ended up in the
blood mimic that of the vitamin D quote
brother from the mushrooms or from the
capsules so I think he's gone a long way
in proving that this actually has a
benefit in the serum and the fact though
that would benefit your immune system
there is no greater yielding plant that
I know growing on her or food source
going on land aquatic systems aside
because they're a different ecosystem
than growing mushrooms on straw for
instance one ton of straw 2,000 pounds
can go about 400 pounds of dried
mushrooms which say you get a 25% so
that conversion of a cellulosic
substrate that has less than a half a
percent nitrogen to a mushroom which has
up to 20 percent nitrogen there is a
nitrogen deficit when you do this
formulas and it's been a conundrum for
mycologist for a long time and that you
end up with more nitrogen at the end of
the process that way than you do at the
beginning but we think that's coming
from nitrogen fixing bacteria which then
the mycelium up channels and uses and
building the mushrooms so when you think
about that a ton of straw you can't eat
any of that straw you know in two to
four weeks you can have hundreds of
pounds of mushrooms that can feed
hundreds of people quarter pound of
mushroom per person you do the math you
can feed a thousand people
you know several meals from one ton of
straw so it's very intensive it's very
fast and moreover that straw then
becomes a mulch that can eat nematodes
and oyster mushrooms are well known to
producing a little lasso that no toads
for whatever reason go through the lasso
and it cinches them and it consumes
nematodes as a food source so nematodes
hurting root crops is a big issue
moisture mushrooms mulching after you
pick the mushrooms we're doing when you
pick the mushrooms benefits the
ecosystem and reducing other parasitic
organisms that can impair other
vegetables mushrooms shiitake maitake
enokitake guna honshimeji there's about
50 to 100 species that we can call a bit
right now only based on that some people
actually is higher than that but
commonly cultivated there's less than 50
species we could be having hundreds of
species some of these grow in snow
layers some of these grow in the hottest
tropics so we have a repertoire of
species to choose within our library of
candidates that can span all seasons
there's two other books the mushroom
cultivator and growing gourmet and
medicinal mushrooms combine this 1,100
pages of intensive information on
substrate preparation and sterile tissue
culture technique mycelium running was
my attempt to try to go away from the
laboratory and they gave mush mushrooms
and natural systems even though the
intensive cultivation of a sterile
tissue culture is really largely
perfected and high guarantee of success
what marshal mycelium grow in the
laboratory does not have the mushroom
mycelium goes in and the natural
environments is an intact immune system
it's the baby in the bubble syndrome so
under cleanroom conditions clean
environments we grow lots of mushrooms
but when you take the mushrooms my
selling amount of laboratory you throw
it in the ground you feed a bunch of
bugs
I think I'll blow it up and so what
mycelium running does talks a lot about
the transitional state of familiarizing
acquainting the immune system
enjoy with a natural microflora so
they're able to withstand being put out
in the nature when you when you were 10
taught you explained to the gardener's
how to transplant stem bucks from Percel
mushrooms so you could actually spread
your crop of Paris on mushrooms could
you explain that briefly it's not fair
it's just not fair that's 35 years
developing sterile tissue culture
techniques and then this technique is so
simple take it and and I think it's I
think you know again we should go back
to nature because this is a good
examples of why this works
many of the stem bucks we click the
mushroom in the wild if you're a bear or
a deer or a person you trim off the stem
by because it got dirt and you want to
eat the mushroom without dirt so we
picked mushrooms we take a few steps we
trim off the stem but we throw it on the
ground turns out their stem butts regrow
with an enormous vigor totally
unexpected the caps won't do that the
caps will rot the stem butts the big
butt of stem becomes mycelium and so you
can put that onto cardboard and create
sheet mulch and the good thing about
that mycelium coming from stem pots it
has an immune system it's already in
tact with the microbes and so it already
has defenses against the pair of
microbial parasites that it's in contact
with then he grows sheets of mycelium
out on wet cardboard corrugated
cardboard and a mycelium grows really
quickly down the corrugations then you
can put wood chips on top of that and
then you end up with a mycelial membrane
a mother patch and then this mother
patch can be put out in along trails and
you end up with veins and the cool thing
about my psyllium this has follows the
path often times of human footsteps
because as we build trails in the woods
we break sticks underneath the mycelium
senses that newly available nutrition so
surges so a lot of these fungi have
actually been following human activity
for thousands of years and so the wood
chip loving the mushrooms including the
philosophy the soul type of mushrooms
are really localized on the debris
fields of humans and it's interesting
that even though species could have very
strong buyer
native properties because of their
illegality and the irrational fear you
know of them being abused irrational in
some cases irrational and others it's
the those species are not in the
limelight but we found that group to be
especially active and breaking down VX
which Saddam Hussein did use against the
Kurds and those mushrooms produce an
enzyme the D phosphorylates dimethyl
methyl phosphonate DM MP which is the
core constituent nerve toxin in VX
specifically psilocybin mushrooms did
that but here's an example where if we
have a mushroom this illegal that will
have a tremendously positive effect that
prevents bioterrorism what side of the
fence are you gonna be on you know it
becomes a complicated endeavor one of
the biggest challenges that we face is
that you mentioned mushrooms people make
fun of you and so I put it to you what
politician will stick their neck out
saying we should invest in mushroom
technologies to help fight bioterrorism
actually the US Defense Department is
cool that they actually see that as
being very plausible and medical
practice and doctors who are in the
knowledge of diseases you know disease
pathogens in particular they get it
mushrooms don't like the rock they
produce a host defensive immunity
against microbes until they sport elated
and after they'd sporty late they rot
but up at that point in time they
forestall many of the same microbial
diseases that afflict us but you come to
a politician and who has a political
career he was in charge of budgets
governments and policy good luck because
the politicians did not want to be made
fun of and if they have a adversary
who's anti nature you know anti
environmentalists then they could use
them as a target and so that's why I
think this is another problem that we
may have the very solutions that save us
from extinction but because of you know
the politics of being
being made fun of we might end up
falling off the faces planet so to speak
ecologically just because we don't want
to look bad we don't be embarrassed that
would be a true irony of human existence
and it may be that we were condemned to